<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The countesse of Mountgomeries Eusebeia expressing briefly, the soules praying robes. By Ro: Nevvton.</title>
            <author>Newton, Robert, b. 1576.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1620</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 99 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 76 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08173</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18509</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120357</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855556</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855556</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21051</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08173)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21051)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 584:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The countesse of Mountgomeries Eusebeia expressing briefly, the soules praying robes. By Ro: Nevvton.</title>
                  <author>Newton, Robert, b. 1576.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 143, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By George Purslow. for A. G[ilman],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1620.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prayer --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21051:1"/>
            <p>THE COVNTESSE OF MOVNTGOMERIES EVSEBEIA: <hi>Expreſſing briefly, THE SOVLES</hi> PRAYING <hi>ROBES.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By Ro: NEVVTON.</p>
            <p>Printed at London by <hi>George Purſtow,</hi> for <hi>A. G.</hi> 1620.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:21051:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21051:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THAT NOBLE ROOT OF HONOVR <hi>AND VERTVE,</hi> THE LADY MARY, <hi>COVNTESSE</hi> OF PEMBROOKE, <hi>AND HER</hi> ILLVSTRIOVS <hi>BRANCHES,</hi> WILLIAM, EARLE OF PEMBROOKE, <hi>LORD</hi> Chamberlaine to his <hi>Maieſtie,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:21051:3"/>
PHILIP, EARLE OF MOVNT<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GOMERY, <hi>WITH THEIR</hi> HONOVRABLE <hi>LADIES, MARY,</hi> COVNTESSE OF <hi>PEMBROOKE,</hi> SVSAN, <hi>COVNTESSE OF</hi> MOVNTGOMERY, AND HER VERTVOVS <hi>Honourable Siſters;</hi> ELIZABETH, <hi>COVNTESSE OF</hi> DARBIE, <hi>AND</hi> BRIDGET, <hi>LADY</hi> NORRIS.</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:21051:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Et it not, I pray you, ſeem ſtrange, that thus I vnite you in this Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation: God him ſelfe hath gone before mee, vniting you in blood af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finity and vertues; and I hope it's no offence to follow his example. The ſubiect of this worke is Piety; whereto as the world doth witneſſe you All to bee adicted, deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb facs="tcp:21051:4"/>your ſelues moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligiouſly to God, in your owne perſons, being pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternes to others of it: ſo ſtill to keepe burning that fire of Goodneſſe, kindled in your hearts, &amp; flaming in your liues, by the power of Gods Spirit ſhed abroad in your ſoules; accept of ſuch helpes as heere you ſhall finde drawn out of the Scriptures, <hi>Gods Armorie,</hi> which if you pleaſe to vſe, you ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:21051:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>finde how <hi>potent</hi> they are in <hi>proſperitie</hi> to keepe you, in <hi>aduerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> to comfort you, and in the day of the Lord to <hi>crowne</hi> you, through the mercy of God, with <hi>Happineſſe</hi> and <hi>Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity:</hi> which Bleſſings, with All elſe, wiſhing to <hi>Euery One</hi> of you, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the multiplying of <hi>All</hi> Graces in you, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, Health, Children, Life to his Glory, Sted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtneſſe in the Faith,
<pb facs="tcp:21051:5"/>comfort and ioy in the Holy Ghoſt, Patience, Wiſedome, Hope and Perſeuerance in All god lines to the end, and the quiet Peace of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence at your end; I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Euer deuoted to</hi> Your Honours in all duties, <hi>Ro: NEVVTON.</hi>
               </signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my Houſe at</hi> Gretford <hi>in</hi> Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colnſhire, <date>May. <hi>20. 1620.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:21051:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE COVNTESSE of <hi>Mountgomeries</hi> Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebeia, expreſſing briefly the Soules praying ROBES.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ow pleaſing and ſweet, in the ſight of our glorious and mercifull God, the ſeruice of Prayer and praiſe is: how com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:21051:6"/>and profitable likewiſe to man, in all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, and times, whether of Affliction, or Ioy, the Scriptures, which are the words &amp; Records of life, &amp; the experience of ſuch, as God by his Spirit hath ſealed vnto life, doe moſt exactly, and eaſily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare.</p>
            <p>In the 50. Pſalme, God cals Prayer a Sacrifice; and ſayes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.23.</note> that whoſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers it vnto him, honours him: And in the 14. verſe layes a command vpon his ſeruants, both to praiſe him, and in the day of trouble to pray vnto him:
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:21051:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>adding a moſt heauenly ſweet promiſe to heare them.</p>
            <p>Now, Sacrifices in the Law, were that peculiar worſhip of God, which himſelfe to ſerue him with. And they were of two ſorts. Either Propitiatory, to appeaſe God for ſinnes committed, or duties o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted: or Euchariſticall, to praiſe God for bleſſings receiued. In the firſt was acknowledged mans guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſe to God: In the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Gods mercy &amp; loue to man: By both, mans obligation to God.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:21051:7"/>
Such a Sacrifice Prayer is. A Propitiatory ſacrifice of a heart, broken and pownded with ſorrow for ſinne: which (through the eternall ſacrifice of Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.28.</note> who offered vp himſelfe once, a full and abſolute Propitiatorie Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice on the Croſſe, for the ſinnes of all that true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repent,) is made accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table in the ſight of God.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.17</note> Wherein in the lippes and tongue are the ſoules In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreters, to let men and Angels know the vnex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſible and vnſearchable grones and ſights of Gods Spirit within vs.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 71.23, 24.</note> For it is
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:21051:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>not enough to haue the heart ſmitten thorow, and wounded with griefe, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe the tongue like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe tell it out to God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.3.</p>
            <p>And as it is a Sacrifice Propitiatorie: ſo is it alſo an Euchariſticall Sacrifice of a heart drawne out, like <hi>Salomons</hi> Curtaines, by the mercy of God, and lifted vp, and filled with the ioy of Heauen, the preſence of the Spirit of God in the ſoule, making it daunce,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 28.7.</note> as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeaks, for ioy: and forcing the tongue to breake out in ſongs, and melodious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioycings,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:21051:8"/>for the pardon of ſinnes paſt;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 57.7, 8, 9, 10, 11.</note> for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and feeling of cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiall grace; for the aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of Gods mercy; for deliuerance from in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant dangers and feares: for graces, and good mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions internall; as Faith, Hope, Loue, hatred of ſinne, care to keep a good Conſcience, watchfulnes, ſpecially ouer the eyes, tongue and heart: for bleſſings externall; as Health, Liberty, Plenty, Peace, Riches, Honour, Children, Friends, Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants fearing God, a good name, long life: For his
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:21051:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>workes of mercy generall and particular on his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, our ſelues, our Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies: for his Iuſtice, iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and plagues vpon the wicked.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Prieſts</hi> that offer this Sacrifice, are not the ſonnes of <hi>Aaron</hi> alone, as once it was in the old Law; but <hi>All,</hi> the children of God euery-where, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed by the bloud of Chriſt, and ſancrified through the power of his reuiuing grace; for hee hath made vs not onely ſonnes of God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.12.</note>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 1.6.</note> but giuen vs the honour to be Kings and Prieſts to God, to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:21051:9"/>and offer, through him, odours, and incenſe, ſweetly ſmelling, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfull in the noſthrils of his Father: yet as <hi>Aaron</hi> might not offer,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exo.</hi> 40.13, 14. <hi>Leu.</hi> 10.1, 2</note> but in his ſacrificing weedes, and nothing, but that which God commanded; no more muſt wee, either in the Congregation, pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquely with the Saints of God, where God enioynes vs to render this ſacrifice;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 100.3. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 96.8, 9. <hi>Math.</hi> 6.6. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 111.1.</note> or in our owne houſes or cloſets priuately, where Chriſt himſelfe hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded vs to make it, doe it ſo, but that he that is in heauen may accept it, and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:21051:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>wee that are on earth may haue comfort of it.</p>
            <p>That this may be done, ſome things are required and neceſſary, before wee offer, ſome in the very time and inſtant of our of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, ſome when wee haue offered this ſacrifice to God.</p>
            <p>Before it,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Chro.</hi> 11.18.</note> goe three du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, like <hi>Dauids</hi> 3. Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies, breaking thorow the ranges of the Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines.</p>
            <p>The firſt, is repentance of all our ſinnes:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 66.16 18.</note> for <hi>If I regard wickedneſſe in my heart</hi> (ſaith <hi>Dauid</hi>) <hi>God will not heare me:</hi> Becauſe, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:21051:10"/>God heares not ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 9.31. that is, ſuch as repent not: but refuſeth their ſacrifice, as hee did the Iewes, <hi>Eſay</hi> 1.11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16. becauſe their hands were full of bloud: and the incenſe of <hi>Sheba,</hi> that is, the beſt and moſt exquiſite words that can be:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 6.20.</note> becauſe their hearts were ſtuffed with euil: yea, the very offerings of the Prieſts themſelues:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Micah</hi> 6.6, 7, 8.</note> 
               <hi>Amos</hi> 5.21, 22. plainely affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, that he that offered ſuch ſacrifice, is as he that ſlayes a man, vgly and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable in his ſight, <hi>Eſay</hi> 66.2.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:21051:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Therefore the holy men were wont in ancient time to practiſe Repentance ere they came to pray, ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their clothes, in ſigne of ſorrow and deteſtation of ſinne; as did <hi>Ezra: Ez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra</hi> 9.3, 5. and <hi>Daniel</hi> in the time of Iſraels captiuitie, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.3. In imitation of whom, it behoue vs to rend our hearts, <hi>Ioel</hi> 2.1. that when wee come to him who was rent for vs,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 53.5.</note> we may haue aſſurance to heare that voice, <hi>Vade, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſa ſunt: Goe thy way, thy ſins are forgiuen thee.</hi> And this is our aſſurance, 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.22. that <hi>whatſoeuer wee
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:21051:11"/>aske of him, wee ſhal receiue, if wee repent and keepe his commandements.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond duty is, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation</hi> with men: A thing as neceſſary before our daily ſacrifice of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, as before the holy ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the Supper. For which cauſe our Sauiour bids vs <hi>agree with our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſarie quickly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 12.28.</note> 
               <hi>whilſt we are in the way:</hi> either in the way of life to death-ward, as <hi>Chryſostome</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds it, or in the way of deuotion to God-ward, as Saint <hi>Bernard,</hi> or in the way of ſinne to hell-ward, as Saint <hi>Ierome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:21051:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
And <hi>Mathew</hi> 5. hee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo commands vs, That when we bring our Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to the Altar, that is, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer vp our oriſons to God, and remember that our Brothers haue ought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs, leaue off our of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, and firſt go and be reconciled, and when wee are at vnity, then make our prayers.</p>
            <p>And if our hearts be ſo bigge, that wee can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther finde in our ſelues a diſpoſition to forgiue, nor ſeeke forgiueneſſe at o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers hands, hee ſpares not to tell vs, that God his Father will ſauce vs,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.15.</note> as we
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:21051:12"/>ſerue others: <hi>If we forgiue others, hee will alſo forgiue vs: but if we will not, nay, if wee doe not, neither will he forgiue vs.</hi> A fearefull ſentence, that the God of all mildneſſe ſhould bee wroth with vs, as long as we are at oddes with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
            <p>Therfore that our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers may pierce the clouds, wee muſt follow Saint <hi>Iames</hi> his counſell, as in hearing the word of God, ſo in ſacrificing praiſe to God;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam</hi> 1.21.</note> and that is, <hi>All filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and ſuperfluity of mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſneſse ſet apart, with meekeneſſe and pure hands,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:21051:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>lift vp our hearts;</hi> not fraught with gall, as was <hi>Cains</hi> to <hi>Abel;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.</note> nor filled with guile, as <hi>Achitophels</hi> to <hi>Dauid;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 6.7.</note> but fired like <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayes,</hi> and fixed like <hi>Dauids</hi> in the Rocke of <hi>Vnity</hi> and <hi>Amity</hi> with God &amp; man:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 108.1.</note> Elſe, if there bee enuying and ſtrife in our hearts, though wee <hi>pray,</hi> yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce not,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jam.</hi> 3.14.</note> for wee are but lyers againſt the truth, witneſſing againſt our ſelues, that we do but play the Hypocrites with God And this wiſedome is not from aboue, but is <hi>earthly, ſenſuall,</hi> and <hi>diuelliſh;</hi> for
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:21051:13"/>where enuying and ſtrife is, there is ſedition and all manner of wickedneſſe: But the wiſedome that is from God, is firſt <hi>pure,</hi> then peaceable, gentle, ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie to bee intreated, full of <hi>mercy and good fruits,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out iudging, and without Hypocriſie: And the fruit of righteouſneſſe is ſowne in peace, of them that make Peace, ſeeking to keep faſt the vnity of Loue in the bond of Peace; when they are to enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the houſe of Peace, to pray to him that is the God of Peace, that whilſt they liue heere, they may
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:21051:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>dwell in Peace; and when they dye, may reſt and reigne in the Kingdome of Peace.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third duty, is a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and ſacred prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to Prayer,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccl.</hi> 18.24</note> that wee may bee able to ſpeake to God. For God is a King of Glory: <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 24.8. and his Throne is ſet: <hi>Dan.</hi> 12. euen a Throne of vnac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſible glory: <hi>Ezech.</hi> 1. from whence hee viewes all the thoughts of Men,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amos.</hi> 4.12. <hi>Ier.</hi> 23.24. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 5.</note> and heares the prayers of all the world.</p>
            <p>For w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> cauſe the wiſeſt <hi>Salomon</hi> aduiſeth, that wee guide well both our Heart
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:21051:14"/>and Tongue, when wee come to ſacrifice praiſe to this God, that we neither bee raſh with our Mouth, nor haſty with our Heart to vtter any thing before God; for God is in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and wee on Earth: And therefore when wee enter into his Houſe, take heed to our feet, our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections hee meanes, the feet of our Soule, and bee readier to heare, that is, to haue thy heart wel pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, rather then to offer the ſacrifice of Fooles.</p>
            <p>Now that wee may bee rightly prepared: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, our minds muſt bee emptyed
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:21051:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>and ſwept of all thoughts &amp; impediments that may hinder this holy Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice. As Chriſt cleered the Temple of the choppers and changers;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.15.</note> ſo muſt we our Soules of all thoughts and affections, whether it bee of profit or pleaſure And if that cannot bee yet at leaſt wee muſt turne them aſide for a time: for worldly thoughts are thoſe floods of Satan, which ſtriue to quench in vs the fire of the Spirit: that vaile, that cloud that blinds and hides vs from ſeeing God. Therefore as <hi>Moſes</hi> put off his Shooes
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:21051:15"/>when hee drew neere the Buſh;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.5.</note> ſo muſt wee all vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holy lets, that with <hi>Dauid</hi> wee may liſten what God will ſay within vs.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, there muſt be an earneſt Meditation,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 145.5. <hi>Gen.</hi> 24.63. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 101.1. <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.1. <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.3. <hi>Mat.</hi> 14.23. <hi>Acts</hi> 10.</note> both of the mercies for which wee muſt praiſe God, and of the bleſſings for which wee muſt pray to God. <hi>Iſaacks</hi> walking, <hi>Dauids</hi> ſinging, <hi>Chriſts</hi> of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten repoſedneſſe in the Wildernes, in the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, <hi>Peters</hi> retiredneſſe, and <hi>Ezechiahs</hi> teares, ſhew this to bee the way to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoid the offering of the ſacrifice of Fooles; and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:21051:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>alſo that fond <hi>Phariſaicall</hi> babbling which Chriſt finds fault with, <hi>Math.</hi> 6.7. wherewith our prayers are too much defiled.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, there muſt be a lifting vp of the Heart &amp; Soule to God:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.1.</note> that as <hi>Elias</hi> fiery Chariot carried him to Heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whilſt <hi>Eliſha</hi> was on Earth: So the zeale of God wrapping vs in a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred fury, may mount our Spirits on the wings of deſire to the very Throne of God, whilſt heere they are encloſed in their houſe of Clay. The Temple of God was ſet on the top of the Hill Sion; ſo that they
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:21051:16"/>that went thither, aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by degrees: to teach vs, that when wee goe to pray, wee muſt learne to goe vp out of our ſelues, not caring to view the beauty of <hi>Ieruſalem;</hi> but to looke on the glittering golden Eaſt gate, and the Cherubims with the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy-feate, the Throne of God, &amp; of the Lamb, that may bring vs as it were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a ſacred extaſie, rauiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our hearts with the brightneſſe of God: for this is it will make vs to dance with <hi>Dauid</hi> before the Arke of God,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Chro.</hi> 15.29.</note> and to cry out with him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 108.1.</note> 
               <hi>Our
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:21051:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>heart is fixed, O God, our heart is fixed: we will ſing and giue praiſe;</hi> crying to the Creatures, the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, the Earth, the Sun,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 148.</note> the Starres, the Angels, and all things to praiſe God with vs, as hee did, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 57.7.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, there muſt be a holy and humble <hi>Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 5.7.</note> of the Maieſty and name of God, in regard of God, of Angels, and men: Of God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amos</hi> 4.12. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.10.</note> for hee ſees our Hearts; of Angels, for they behold our carriage, our order, our demea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; of Men, for they are apt to take example:
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:21051:17"/>the good to imitate, the rebellious to ſcoffe, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps to reuile; yea, and it may be,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.25.</note> (for ſo Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſayes) to be wonne by.</p>
            <p>And this reuerence, as it muſt not bee hypocriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call (for then God abhors it) nor ſuperſtitious, (for hee will diſdaime it:) So muſt it come from a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite heart that trembles at his words;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 66.2.</note> (yet not with a ſlauiſh feare, but humbled at the preſence of him that reſiſts the proud:) and a ſetled geſture and comely carriage of the whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, that may expreſſe the inward meekneſſe and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:21051:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſtayedneſſe of the mind.</p>
            <p>Elſe ſhall wee doe but as the Phariſe did,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 18.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuouſly come to the Temple of the mighty God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Leuit.</hi> 10.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and with <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu,</hi> offer vp ſtrange fire, loathſome and fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe prayers to God, who in ſtead of hearing, will ſtop his eares, ſince we are vnfitted to ſpeake to him, and in ſtead of bleſſings, will raine downe croſſes, if not curſes vpon vs, ſince we are ſo impudently bold to abuſe him.</p>
            <p>The want of due regard to theſe things, oftentimes makes the houſe of God,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:21051:18"/>the houſe of <hi>Rimmon;</hi> or as Chriſt ſaid, <hi>A Den of Theeues,</hi> where <hi>vnrepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants</hi> and <hi>relapſers,</hi> ill ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued &amp; diueliſh-minded <hi>Shemeis,</hi> railing and black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth'd <hi>Rabſhaka's,</hi> proud and inſulting <hi>Hamans,</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſte &amp; adulterous <hi>Ieſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels,</hi> falſe and damned ſlie <hi>Achitophels,</hi> hypocriticall <hi>Ahabs,</hi> murtherous <hi>Ioabs,</hi> laſciuious whoriſh <hi>Iehu's,</hi> hell-bred <hi>Nicolaitans,</hi> ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious <hi>Micah's,</hi> &amp; all the ſinfull rabble of men, with eyes full of adultery, with hands full of cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, with hearts full of all impiety, impinitencie; hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:21051:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>malignitie, ebri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etie, and tongues tipt with the poyſon of Aſps; open their mouthes, and bend (perhaps) their knees, (which many of them think themſelues too good to doe) and powre forth like <hi>Bels Prieſts,</hi> abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation in ſtead of a ſweet ſmelling Sacrifice, <hi>heaping thereby, vpon their owne pates, wrath</hi> as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſayes, <hi>againſt the day of wrath,</hi> in that when they come to ſee and ſpeake to God, a God hating wickedneſſe, a God dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in light, a God whoſe voyce ſhakes the very hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:21051:19"/>and whoſe eye-lids reade the ſecrets of their ſoules, they haue not with <hi>Moſes</hi> put off their ſhoos, nor with <hi>Aaron</hi> put on their ſacrificing weeds; but either naked like <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.</note> they appeare before God; or, if they bee clad, it is but with the ragges of vnrighteouſneſſe, not with the rich attire of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration. And therefore, as he without a Wedding garment receiued his ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Kings mouth, at the Table, in preſence of the gheſts, to be taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, bound, &amp; thrown in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Hel; ſo they, for offering
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:21051:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>the ſacrifice of <hi>Fooles,</hi> fooles as they are, that is, wicked and lewd men, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the iuſt reward of their ſinne; which is, that when they pray, they are neuer heard, except it bee to their further condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; and hauing pray'd, they are neuer beuered, but rather worſe in their conuerſation. The vnduti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and vnreuerent beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour of many, young, el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and eldeſt of all in the ſacred houſe of God, in the time of publique pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and thankſgiuing to God; ſome moſt vnreue re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly capp'd, whilſt others
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:21051:20"/>doe, &amp; they ſhould, but do not, pray and ſing to God, ſome not vouchſafing ſo much as to bend one knee to God, (a token that their hearts are vnfit to bow,) ſome whiſpering and tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to others, ſome ſnor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and ſleeping before the Angels of God; ſome reading and not ioyning with the Miniſter and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in ſeruing God, ſome not content to bee ſlack themſelues, but to hinder others from comming to God, ſome ſpeaking e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, like wicked <hi>Iulian</hi> and wretched <hi>Lucian,</hi> of the worſhip of God, ſome
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:21051:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>carping at the Miniſter, ſome at the Seruice, ſome at the Seates, ſome at the Ceremonies in the Church of God, ſome ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer publikely nor priuate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inuoking<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> God, too plainly giues euidence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the looſeneſſe of the time, and ſhewes vs the cauſe why our Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice is not accepted of God; becauſe like <hi>Cain</hi> wee are hollow toward God.</p>
            <p>Firſt therefore for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, let vs learne of <hi>Dauid</hi> to waſh our hands in innocencie and ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to the Altar of God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 26.6.</note>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:21051:21"/>remembring with Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De 10. chord. c. 5. Aug. lib. de Eccl. dog. cap. 48.</note> that Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance frees vs from the wrath of God, and aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth all our ſinnes. Now if the fleſh, which is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies vnwilling, thinke it too burdenous, ſo oft to repent as we pray to God, know that as the ſame fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſayes,<note place="margin">De 10. chordis.</note> It's better a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to be puniſhed heere, then to bee plagued euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtingly in Hell. Know al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that Repentance is the yoke of Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.29.</note> which him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſayes is eaſie, and he it is, that by the aſſiſtance of his grace helps thee to beare it. Know it is the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:21051:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>chiefeſt marke of Gods children,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.23.</note> to bee groning and repining, and repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of their ſinne: not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pining againſt God, but their owne corrupt heart, that is alwayes betraying the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into the power of ſin. Know laſtly, that whoſo repents not, cannot pray, becauſe the ſpirit of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7, 10, 11.</note> and the grace of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, ſorrow for ſin, deteſtation of ſinne, care to auoid ſinne, comfort a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſinne, are inſepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble one from another; ſo as none can repent, but they can cry, but they can pray, but they can truſt,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:21051:22"/>but they can hope, but they can hang vpon the promiſes of God euen with <hi>Iob,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 19.26.</note> in deſpight of Hell, relying on God, and with <hi>Peter</hi> powring out true teares of ſighes and ſobbes vnto God.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.75</note> And till we finde in ſome good meaſure, ſome of theſe graces begotten in vs, bee not too ſecure; our caſe is not ſo good as we take it for: And therefore when wee meane to ſacrifice to God, take heed wee firſt make our agreement with him.</p>
            <p>And for Reconciliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with our Brethren:
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:21051:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>Since God hath reſolu'd not to be reconciled to vs, till we firſt be recouciled with them, and for that cauſe taught vs to pray him to forgiue vs as wee doe them;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.15.</note> let there bee no rancour in our mindes when wee pray: for as <hi>Iſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore</hi> ſaies,<note place="margin">Lib. de ſummo bono. c. 27</note> In vaine doe they ſeeke to bee at one with God, that needs will be at ods with their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. Therefore, if thy brother haue offended thee, goe, ere thou pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, and bee reconciled: if hee be farre off, and thou canſt not come at him, then muſt thou goe (ſaies
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:21051:23"/>Saint <hi>Auſtin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De. 10. chord. c. 5.</note> with the feet of thy heart where thou maiſt finde him; proſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thy affections hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to God, crauing ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly pardon at his hands. But if thou canſt ſpeake with him, thou muſt pray pardon of him, whom thou haſt wronged: Saint <hi>Gregory</hi> tels thee how, and ſo Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> on <hi>Math.</hi> 5. If thou haſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended by thought, in thinking ill of him, bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled in thought, by thinking well of him: if by words thou haſt hurt him, by words thou muſt ſlake him: if by deeds thou haſt
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:21051:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>wronged him, by deeds thou muſt make amends; for thou canſt not other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then by deeds be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned at him, whom by deeds thou haſt wronged. In vaine is thy Sacrifice of Prayer of Almes, when thou offereſt that which is wrongfully got: And what can it profit thee, that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers pray for thee, and thou all the while prayeſt againſt thy ſelfe? The moſt high regards not the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of <hi>Cain.</hi> I will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this poynt with that ſaying of S. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> vpon thoſe words, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. <hi>Forgiue vs our treſpaſſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:21051:24"/>
Wouldſt thou haue God to bee no otherwiſe good to thee, but only not to hurt thee; and yet turne away his face and cheerefull countenance from thee, alwaies ſetting thy ſinnes in his ſight, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies thinking of thine iniquities, and not once vouchſafing to looke vpon thee? Surely, O man, thou wouldeſt not for a world. Such therefore as thou wouldſt haue God bee to thee when thou prayeſt for pardon of thy ſinnes, ſuch muſt thou be to thine offending brother.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, for Preparation:
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:21051:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>Since the Church of God is the houſe of glory;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 11.</note> and God in his Church doth ſhew his glory, ſince the Angels of God,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.10.</note> which are full of glory, attend on thy ſacrifice and marke all thy deeds; ſince the powers of Hell bend and their powers then moſt to hinder thee,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.1.</note> when thou ſhouldſt pray moſt publikely, priuately, by thy ſelfe, with others, abroad, at home, in all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands: As the Iſraelites in the Wilderneſſe at the giuing of the Law, were prepared to heare God ſpeake to them:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 19.12.</note> and <hi>Moſes</hi>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:21051:25"/>when hee ſaw the vnburnt burning buſh,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.5.</note> put off his ſhooes: Bee thou, when thou commeſt to ſpeake vnto God, prepared ſo, that neither thine Eye may miſlead thy Heart, nor thy Heart may faile thy Tongue, nor thy Tongue either babble with the Phariſes long,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 6.7.</note> and to little purpoſe, or liſpe like the Ephramites,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iudg.</hi> 12.6.</note> ſpeake thy minde imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly and vnaptly to God: But that the whole man, <hi>body</hi> and <hi>ſoule,</hi> with a ſanctified heauenly reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of God, in regard of his bleſſings, for which
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:21051:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>thou muſt praiſe him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 117.</note> and of his mercies, for which thou muſt pray to him, as alſo of his iudgements, for which thou muſt feare him, and of his wiſdome, for which thou muſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour him, may bee offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vp, together with thy prayſes, a holy acceptable Sacrifice to God: And this is our reaſonable ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of God.</p>
            <p>Now as before our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice-offering, theſe are the robes more rich and glorious then thoſe of <hi>Aaron,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 39.</note> wherein our Soules ſhould bee arrayed, if when wee come to the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:21051:26"/>Altar of God, we would haue our Prayers goe vp like the incenſe: So in the time whilſt wee are in of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, I find in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and the practice of the Saints, ſome other or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>náments that muſt bee v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, as needfull euery one in the time of Prayer, as the former be before.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The firſt is, that euery requeſt wee make to God, muſt proceed from a liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſence,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.</note> feeling, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of the want of that which wee aske: for example; In the firſt Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition, when wee pray that Gods name may be ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified;
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:21051:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>that is, that in his Word, workes, mercies, iudgements, and all the creatures wee may glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie him, except wee ſee and feele how proud and blinde, how hard-hearted and ingratefull wee are to God by nature, and alſo by cuſtome in ſinne, for his mercies, for his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, for his Word, for his Spirit, &amp;c. wee can neuer pray ſeriouſly for humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, for the true knowledge of God, for zeale, for loue, for care to pleaſe God; all which, and more, are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded in this Petition.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond Petition,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:21051:27"/>when wee pray and ſay, <hi>Thy Kingdome come,</hi> who can-rightly with feruencie of Spirit, requeſt God to renew his ſoule, his heart, his will and affections, to ſanctifie him ſo, that the ſpirit that raiſed vp <hi>Ieſus</hi> from the graue, may raiſe him from the graue of ſin, and reigne and rule in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery part of him, making him liue in holineſſe and righteouſneſſe all his life, if firſt hee feele not the bondage and heauy yoke of his ſinne, and the ſlaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry wherein naturally he is chain'd to Satan, being dayly led captiue to all
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:21051:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>kinde of vice? Gold and heartleſſe is that requeſt, that flowes not from a true touch of want.</p>
            <p>So in the third, <hi>Thy will bee done,</hi> except wee feele, and that very liuely, our owne proneneſſe and apt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to rebell againſt Gods lawes, our hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, our pride, ambition, contempt of God, his Word and Sacraments, our exaction, oppreſſion, cruelty, impatience and murmuring againſt God becauſe wee cannot haue our owne wills, who can rightly deſire to learne that of Chriſt, to deny
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:21051:28"/>our ſelues, take vp our croſſe daily, ſubmitting our ſelues in all things to God, indeuouring both to know his will and do it?</p>
            <p>In the fourth likewiſe, who can,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 30.8.</note> with <hi>Agur,</hi> pray for contentednes in all eſtates, aſwell pouerty as proſperity, that firſt feeles not a want therof through couetouſneſſe that's natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally ingrafted in him, and diffidence that God will not prouide for him?</p>
            <p>This liuely ſenſe of want was in <hi>Anna,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.10.</note> when in the anguiſh of her heart ſhee praied for a child to God: &amp; in <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.</note> when he roar'd
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:21051:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>for the very torture and vexation of heart, becauſe he felt not Gods preſence and comfort,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 130.1</note> as hee was wont: In <hi>Daniel</hi> alſo,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.</note> when with that feruencie of zeale, he prayed for <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> the Temple, the <hi>Iewes</hi> and himſelfe, after their long Captiuity in <hi>Babylon:</hi> And this muſt needs bee in euery one of vs, if like <hi>Elias,</hi> wee would haue our prayers to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ualie.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. And as there muſt be a ſenſe of want,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55.17. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.10.</note> ſo muſt our requeſts proceed alſo from a liuely and feruent deſire; ſuch a one as was
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:21051:29"/>in <hi>Moſes,</hi> when hee ſpake not a word, and yet the Lord asked him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.15.</note> why hee cryed vnto him? when in his heart hee onely called on him. The ſame was in <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 143.</note> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 42.1.2. <hi>As the Hart panteth after the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of water; ſo longs my Soule after thee, O God: My Soule is at hirſts for God, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen for the liuing God? O when ſhall I enter into the preſence of God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 37.16</note> So in <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kias</hi> that noble King, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with bended knees and teares he ſtretched out his hands, and ſpread <hi>Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacheribs</hi> raylings before God.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:21051:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. Further, that our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice may not be like <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſau's,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 27.34.</note> who felt roard and praid when the Birth-right was gone, and that with bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſſe for a bleſſing: nor like <hi>Ahabs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Ki.</hi> 21.27.</note> which was fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent, but yet hypocriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call; euery requeſt wee make to God, muſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed of a liuely faith, by which wee muſt haue an aſſurance to be heard. For they that pray, muſt haue an affiance that God in Chriſt will grant their petitions. For this cauſe Chriſt tells vs,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mark.</hi> 11.24.</note> that <hi>what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer wee deſire when wee
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:21051:30"/>pray, beleeue that wee ſhall haue it, and it ſhall bee done vnto vs.</hi> And Saint <hi>Iames</hi> bids,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.6.</note> 
               <hi>Aske in faith and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer not, and wee ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue our deſires.</hi> And <hi>Chriſt</hi> againe, <hi>Math.</hi> 7.7. <hi>Aske, and yee ſhall receiue.</hi> And <hi>Iohn</hi> 16.23. <hi>Whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer yee aske the Father in my name, he will giue it you.</hi> But alwayes the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is, that we aske in faith. I, but you will ſay, there's all the doubt; for how may I know that I haue faith?</p>
            <p>I purpoſe not heere to handle at large the nature and properties of a liuing
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:21051:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>faith: but onely to ſatisfie the weake and wauering in a word or two, I'le teach you to know faith.</p>
            <p>As Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſayes,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.8.</note> 
               <hi>There are three that beare witneſſe in Heauen, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Word, and the Spirit, and theſe three are One: And there are</hi> 3. <hi>that beare witneſſe in Earth, the</hi> Spirit, <hi>and</hi> Water, <hi>and</hi> Blood, <hi>and theſe</hi> 3. <hi>agree in one:</hi> So Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſayes,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.13.</note> 
               <hi>There are</hi> 3. <hi>that abide in one; Faith, Hope, and Loue, and theſe</hi> 3. <hi>giue witnes vnto one, that Chriſt Ieſus dwells in him.</hi> Faith <hi>witneſſeth with the Spirit
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:21051:31"/>vnto vs, that wee are the Children of God, Rom.</hi> 8.16. And hope and loue wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe vnto faith, that it is a true and liuing faith: as breath, heate and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion witneſſe and approue that the body is aliue: ſo loue and hope approue vnto our hearts that our faith is aliue. There is a dead faith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 2.26.</note> a faith without workes, a faith without hope and loue, the two in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible companions of true faith: But true and liuing faith, which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> calls the faith of the Sonne of God, becauſe he by his Spirit begets it
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:21051:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>in vs, and is the proper ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect of it, hath alwayes with it hope and loue, by which the effects and power of it appeares, to God, to Angels, to Men: to God firſt; then to man: To God,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. In beleeuing his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes made vnto vs in Chriſt.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 16.31.</note>
               </item>
               <item>2. In ſeeing our lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table eſtate by nature,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.1.</note> how we ſtand ſubiect to his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall wrath, eternall death, eternall bondage vnder ſinne and Satan.</item>
               <item>3. In ſorrowing for our ſins generall &amp; particular.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.11.</note>
               </item>
               <item>4. In confeſſing them<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.6.</note>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:21051:32"/>vnto God:</item>
               <item>5. Praying for, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of pardon for Chriſt his ſake:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 2.37.</note>
               </item>
               <item>6. In hungring after righteouſneſſe:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.6.</note>
               </item>
               <item>7. In continually ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoring to hate ſinne,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 2.42.</note> and pleaſe God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 97.10.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Againe, as it's working by loue and hope to God; ſo alſo it's approuing it ſelfe to Angels and Men, by humility and meeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.29.</note> for true faith is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer proud:<note place="margin">1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.14.</note> by patience and long ſuffering; for it murmures not: by chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and almes deeds, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the talent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:21051:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>from God, either by actuall relieuing, or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionate deſiring to doe ſo, viſiting the ſicke,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 25.35, 36.</note> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forting the comfortleſſe, helping the poore, cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing the naked, and in a word, neuer reſting to doe <hi>All good;</hi> not enuying,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.</note> not boaſting, not rayling, not ſpeaking il, not diſdaining, nay, not ſeeking her owne things; not couetous, not laſciuious, not wickedly an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, not thinking ill, not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioycing in any ſin; But ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers all things, indures all things, beleeues all things, and hopes all things:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.16, 17, 18, 19.</note> with <hi>Abraham</hi> it's conſtant in
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:21051:33"/>beleeuing and obeying God;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 8.13.20, 28.</note> with <hi>Paul</hi> it's vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant, in ſuffring all croſſes, all afflictions for God; with <hi>Dauid</hi> it's patient, in all calamities hanging ſtill on God:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 19.25.</note> with <hi>Iob</hi> euen in the fire of triall, and the boyling furnace of Satans ſifting, it cleaues faſt vnto and holds by God; and euery day growes from ſtrength to ſtrength,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.7.</note> bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd in knowledge, bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd in affection, better'd in obedience, till at laſt it come to ſay with <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 23.4.</note> 
               <hi>Thought I walke in the val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley of the ſhadow of death, I will not feare;</hi> and with
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:21051:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>Saint <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 8.38. <hi>Nothing can ſeperate mee from Chriſt Ieſus;</hi> becauſe with <hi>Iob,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 19.25, 26.</note> 
               <hi>it knowes that our Redeemer liues, and that we ſhall riſe vp againe with him to glory.</hi> This, this is that true and liuing faith, wherewith wee muſt offer our ſacrifice to God.</p>
            <p>But if any finde not in their hearts theſe things, nor theſe fruits of faith in their liues, know yet for their comfort, that there is a leſſer degree of a true and liuing faith; which though it be compared to ſmoaking flaxe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 42.2.</note> &amp; a brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed reed, for the weakenes
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:21051:34"/>of it, yet is it a moſt ſure Anchor-hold, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiues perfect acceptance with God.</p>
            <p>And this little faith is, when though, wee know not Gods promiſes of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation by Chriſt exactly; neither are able to apply them to our ſelues perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ſtrongly, as <hi>Paul,</hi> and <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 23. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.38. <hi>Acts</hi> 16.30. <hi>Luke.</hi> 3.10, 12, 14. <hi>Acts</hi> 2.37.</note> and others did; yet wee doe earneſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to repent, and haue our ſinnes pardoned, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king by all meanes of faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, praying, weeping, wiſhing, and conferring with ſuch as are able to help vs, to bee reconciled
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:21051:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>to God, hoping of his mercy, and thirſting after righteouſneſſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.1.</note> &amp; dayly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing in grace, ſtill ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king better &amp; better pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe in Religion.</p>
            <p>Such a faith as this once was in the Apoſtles, the very attendants, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall companions of Chriſt; who though they beleeued Chriſt to be the Sonne of God, <hi>Math.</hi> 16.16. yet they knew not of his Death and Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on till afterward, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6.6. <hi>Math.</hi> 17.23. <hi>Luke</hi> 9.45. <hi>Iohn</hi> 20.9.</p>
            <p>Such alſo was the faith of thoſe Diſciples at <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:21051:35"/>whom <hi>Paul</hi> found ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of the very being of the Holy Ghoſt, by whom they had receiued power and grace to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue in Chriſt.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 19.2.</note> And they that haue this Faith, though but little &amp; ſmall, as wanting the fulneſſe of that ſtrength, by which they might be able to ſay with <hi>Paul,</hi> that they are aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured there's layd vp for them a crowne of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.7, 8.</note> which God will giue them at the laſt day; yet may they with bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and confidence haue acceſſe to the Throne of grace: For GOD hath
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:21051:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>promiſed, that to him that is athirſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 21.6.</note> he will giue of the Well of the water of Life freely. And our Sauiour himſelfe cryed it once in the great day of the great Feaſt of Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacles, that All that are thirſty ſhould come to him and drinke:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 7.37.</note> And if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny be laden with the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of ſinne,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.28.</note> Come vnto him, and he wil eaſe them: For thirſting after righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.6.</note> and remiſſion of ſinnes, is one of the chiefe of thoſe mercies of God, which whoſo hath, alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die is become partaker of eternall happineſſe, and
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:21051:36"/>in the end ſhall bee fully ſatisfied.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 4. Yet now, though we haue faith liuely and true, from which our requeſts muſt proceede; this faith of ours muſt haue his warrant, his ground, his ſtay from the Word of God: So that euery Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition which Faith puts vp, muſt bee made according to the will of God. So Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.14.</note> 
               <hi>Whatſoeuer wee aske in his Name, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his will,</hi> we ſhall receiue. Otherwiſe wee may aske,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 4.3.</note> as Saint <hi>Iames</hi> ſayes, and not receiue, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we aske amiſſe; that
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:21051:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>is, hauing neither com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement ſo to aske, nor promiſe to receiue. And ſo ask'd the Mother of <hi>Zebedees</hi> children pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion for her ſonnes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.23.</note> &amp; was repell'd of Chriſt, becauſe ſhe begged ſhee knew not what. And ſo did <hi>Peter</hi> in Mount <hi>Tha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor</hi> to build Tabernacles.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke.</hi> 9.33. <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.38</note> And the Iewes to ſee a ſigne from Chriſt. Wee therefore that ſacrifice, and that with faith, muſt from God looke for both a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement to war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, and a promiſe to ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill our requeſts.</p>
            <p>And here wee muſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:21051:37"/>two Caueats:</p>
            <p>Firſt, that all our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts to God are either for things ſpirituall or temporall: And ſpirituall things are either abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly neceſſarie to ſaluation; as, the knowledge of God in Chriſt: the remiſsion of ſinnes: Faith, Hope, Loue, Humilitie, Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, a good conſcience, &amp;c. or elſe they are but onely ſuch as are profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: as the vnderſtanding of all Scripture: all know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Arts: Tongues: power to worke miracles, and ſuch like: Thoſe that are of abſolute neceſſitie
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:21051:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>to ſaluation, wee muſt aske them ſimply without condition: So did <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.17.</note> 
               <hi>Dauid, Stephen,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Thoſe that are but profitable, and tempora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, as health, honour, children, life, &amp;c. muſt alwayes haue a condition annexed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.15.</note> If it be for Gods glory: If it be agreeable to his will, <hi>Luke</hi> 22.42.</p>
            <p>Secondly, wee muſt not binde God to any cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of time, place,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 130.5, 6, 7.</note> meanes, or otherwiſe; but leaue all free to him, and with patience attend his pleaſure, as <hi>Dauid</hi> did:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40.1.</note> who waited patiently vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:21051:38"/>the Lord, till hee incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to him. For ſo God commands vs, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 37.3, 4, 5, 6. <hi>Tarry thou the Lords leiſure, and hee will bring it to paſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 5. Fiftly, as we muſt pray from a liuely ſence of our want, with feruent deſire, and a liuely Faith, hauing a warrant from the Word of God, not asking things vnlawful,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 99.5, 6 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 86.7, 8, 9, 10. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.6. <hi>Eſay</hi> 45.5. <hi>Ier.</hi> 23.24. <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.13.</note> nor ſtinting God to any time; ſo this ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice muſt bee offered <hi>onely to God;</hi> ſith <hi>He alone</hi> at all times, and in all places, is able, and can heare <hi>All men,</hi> which neither An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell, nor Saints can doe.
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:21051:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>Secondly, becauſe Prayer and Inuocation, is from Man to God, a peculiar part of Gods honour:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.10.</note> And his honour he hath ſworne not to giue to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 97.7.</note> In which reſpect, the Angell refuſed adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Reuel.</hi> 22.9. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding vs to worſhip God alone. And GOD himſelfe, by <hi>Dauid,</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to all the Nations of the earth, bids them <hi>truſt in Him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 62.8.</note> 
               <hi>and powre cut their hearts before him.</hi> And in another Pſalme, <hi>Dauid</hi> attributes it for a ſpeciall tythe to God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 65.2.</note> 
               <hi>Thou that heareſt the prayer, vnto thee
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:21051:39"/>ſhall all fleſh come.</hi> For which cauſe that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement is in the 50. <hi>Pſalme</hi> 15. <hi>Call vpon mee,</hi> not on any creature, <hi>in the day of calamitie, and I will help, ſaith God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſure if the Angels muſt not bee honoured with this ſacrifice of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and praiſe, who are glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ſpirits, and more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent by Creation and Grace than the Saints, and are euer with vs,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.14.</note> &amp; about vs for our good, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to that of <hi>Dauid:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.7.</note> 
               <hi>The Angell of the Lord tarry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth round about them that feare him, to deliuer them:</hi>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:21051:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>and that of Chriſt touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing little Infants,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.10</note> 
               <hi>Their Angels alwayes behold the face of their Father which is in Heauen;</hi> much leſſe muſt we pray to any of the Saints, who are neither ſo excellent, nor ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with vs.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 63.16</note> 
               <hi>Abraham knowes vs not,</hi> ſaith God by the Prophet, and <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el is ignornat of vs.</hi> And Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Romanes</hi> proues by demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.14</note> that wee muſt pray <hi>onely to God:</hi> Thus; Hee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone in whom wee muſt beleeue, muſt bee prayed vnto: Onely in God wee muſt beleeue. To him
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:21051:40"/>onely wee muſt therefore pray.</p>
            <p>And to whom elſe did the Fathers, Patriarkes, and Prophets, <hi>Adam, Seth, Henoch, Noah, Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Dauid, Daniel, Eſay, Ieremy</hi> in the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp; Chriſt himſelf, the Apoſtles, and the Church in the new, euer tender this ſacrifice of Prayer, &amp; praiſe, but to the moſt Higheſt God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.6.</note> the Father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I haue cryed vnto thee, O LORD,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 130.1. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 146.1. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 5.1, 2, 3, 7.</note> ſayes <hi>Dauid, and vnto thee will I giue thankes, for thou art my God.</hi> And when <hi>Ezechia</hi>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:21051:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>in his ſtraitneſſe and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe, prayed, began hee not, <hi>O Lord of Hosts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 37.16.</note> 
               <hi>God of Iſrael, which dwelleſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Cherubims?</hi> Could <hi>Moſes,</hi> or <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> or the Angels haue holpen them, or had they had any confidence in them, they might as well haue prayed vnto them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, as to God.</p>
            <p>It is therefore a ſpirit of errour and deluſion, that perſwades poore igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants to pray to, and truſt in Saints: And of ſuch ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits we muſt take heede.</p>
            <p>And if the power of Scripture cannot moue
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:21051:41"/>ſuch as are ſimple to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware: heare a little ſhort diſcourſe of Saint <hi>Auſtens,</hi> which word for word, I will ſet downe, out of his Booke of taking care for the Dead: the thirteenth Chapter.</p>
            <p>If the ſoules of the dead could be, or were preſent, at or about the affayres of the liuing, and ſpeake vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, when we dreame in our ſleepe wee ſee them; ſurely, my Holy Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther no night would for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake mee, who followed mee both by Sea and Land to liue with me. For God forbid, that by ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:21051:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>a happier life, ſhee ſhould now become more vnkinde then ſhe was; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch, as when my heart is vexed and filled vvith ſorrow, ſhee will not ſo much as comfort her ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grieued ſonne, whom ſhe loued moſt dearly, whom ſhee neuer could endure willingly to ſee ſad. But ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, it it as the Pſalmiſt ſayes, <hi>My Father and my Mother haue forſaken mee, but the Lord hath taken mee vp.</hi> If then our Fathers haue left vs; how are they preſent and behold our cares? And if our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers bee not: what other
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:21051:42"/>dead folkes are there that know what wee doe, or what wee ſuffer? And a little after, The Spirits of the Dead are in ſuch a place, as they doe not ſee the occurrences &amp; things in this life.</p>
            <p>If neither they ſee vs then, nor know not what we doe: ſure heare vs they cannot: and why then ſhould wee pray to them? Let Chriſts anſwer to the Diuel ſticke in our hearts, when wee are tempted to pray to them;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.10.</note> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt worſhip the Lord thy God, and Him onely thou ſhalt ſerue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:21051:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> 6. Beſides, as God one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly muſt haue this Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.15</note> ſo wee muſt offer it not in our owne, but in the name and mediation of Chriſt.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.</note> For we are but duſt and aſhes: of our ſelues vnworthy to come in Gods preſence. Hee it is that is that Lambe of God that hath taken away the ſinnes of the world,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.29.</note> in whom alone god is vvell pleaſed:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.17.</note> Who euer hath this golden Cenſor to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer vpon the golden Altar w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> is before the Throne of God in Heauen,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 8.3, 4.</note> the Prayers of the Faithfull, that they beeing mingled
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:21051:43"/>with the ſweet obours of his Interceſsion and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, the ſmoke of them may aſcend vp before God, <hi>Reu.</hi> 8.3. Therefore Saint <hi>Paul</hi> giues a precept,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 3.17.</note> that whatſoeuer wee doe in word or deed, whether it bee praying or praiſing, or working the workes of this life, or the workes of grace, doe all in the name of the Lord <hi>Ieſus,</hi> giuing thankes to God the Father by <hi>Him.</hi> For he it is alone, in whoſe bloud the Saints waſh their long vvhite Robes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 7.14.</note> through whom we haue acceſſe w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fidence vnto the Throne of grace;
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:21051:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>who by himſelfe hath pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged our ſinnes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.2.</note> and now ſits on the right hand of the Maieſtie of God, to appeare now in the ſight of God for vs.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.24.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Erroneous therefore and derogatory to Chriſt is that doctrin, that teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth other Interceſſors be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides Chriſt:<note place="margin">1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.3. <hi>Iohn</hi> 14.13. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.3. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.25. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.2. <hi>Acts</hi> 9.14.</note> Since there is no name in Heauen, Earth, or elſewhere, but the holy and reuerend name of <hi>Ieſu</hi> onely, in which wee can expect to be heard. Therefore <hi>Onely</hi> in his name muſt this ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice bee made.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> 7 I, but though it bee
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:21051:44"/>made in the name of Chriſt, to God alone, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his will, with a liuely faith, a feruent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, and a ſound ſence of want; yet oftentimes wee ſee, that Gods deareſt children receiue many put-byes:<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.8.</note> as Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> when hee prayed and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſought God thrice to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer him from the meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger of Satan. And the woman of Canaan, when for her Daughter ſhee followed Chriſt, and in all humbleneſſe moſt lowly beſought him, and he would not heare her, no, nor ſo much as looke
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:21051:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>vpon her: nay, when his Diſciples, entreated for her, and ſhee ſtill conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued her requeſt, in ſtead of Myrrh fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe ſweet lippes of his, came forth a bitter gall of diſtaſte; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch as hee ſpared not to call her Dogge.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.26</note> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in offering this holy Sacrifice, which ſo tends to the honour of God, we muſt haue another thing, as it were, to conquer God, when our prayers ſeeme not to pierce his eares: And that, ſayth Chriſt, is <hi>Continuance</hi> and <hi>Perſeucrance</hi> in Prayer: <hi>Luke</hi> 18.1, 7, 8. Whereto
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:21051:45"/>he exhorts vs by a Parable of a Widdow, who by her importunitie wreſted an vniuſt Iudge, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther feared God, nor ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for man, to auenge her of her Aduerſary-Which Parable Saint <hi>Luke</hi> ſets a note vpon; That he did of purpoſe propound to this end, that wee ought <hi>to pray, and not waxe weary, verſe</hi> 1. though God ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer long before hee heare vs, <hi>verſe</hi> 7. This alſo he teacheth by his owne ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, in continuing for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie dayes faſting and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Wilderneſſe, <hi>Math.</hi> 4.1. and whole
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:21051:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>nights in the Mountaines,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 14.23.</note> ſequeſtring himſelfe from all company, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.12.</p>
            <p>By precept likewiſe: <hi>Aske, Seeke, Knocke:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.7.</note> And by another Parable, of one that made his friend, through his importunity,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 11.8.</note> to riſe in the night to giue him Bread: and laſtly, by promiſe, <hi>Math.</hi> 7.7. <hi>Yee ſhall haue: ye ſhall be heard: ye ſhall finde: the doore ſhall be opened.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this <hi>Perſeuerance</hi> we haue for Patters almoſt all the Worthies in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.24</note> 
               <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Iacob,</hi> who all night wreſtled with
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:21051:46"/>God in likeneſſe of a man, and at laſt preuailed.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exo.</hi> 17.12</note> 
               <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> that would neuer giue out: but when hee vvas weary, had <hi>Aaron</hi> and <hi>Hur</hi> to hold vp his hands. <hi>Iob,</hi> and <hi>Danid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69.1, 2, 3. <hi>Act.</hi> 2.1.</note> &amp; the Church in Babylon, the Apoſtles, the Primitiue Church, and all the Martyrs, thoſe Heroick braue Champi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, whoſe mouthes, nor flames;<note place="margin">Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret. Hiſt. Eccl. So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates, Euſebius.</note> nor Lyons iawes, nor any tortures could ſtop from powring out prayers, and ſinging euen in their ſharpeſt pangs, till God and his Chriſt had gotten victory.</p>
            <p>Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> reports
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:21051:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>of his Mother <hi>Monica,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Libris co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> feſsionum, 5.7.8.9.</note> that Noble, Vertuous, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Matron, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeeres together, before God conuerted him, ſhee ſpent whole nights in prayers and teares to God for him,<note place="margin">Lib. conf. 3. c. 11.</note> who as then was no better than an Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous Pagan, for 9. yeeres together (as himſelfe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth) an hereticall Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nichee:<note place="margin">De morib. Ecc. Cath. l. 1. c. 18.</note> And at laſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to a Reuerend Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop,<note place="margin">Lib. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsionum 3. c. 12.</note> &amp; with many teares often moſt inſtantly deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring him, ſeruently to commend her Sonne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God: Hee ſeeing her Teares, her continuance,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:21051:47"/>her holy deſires, cheered her thus vp with this No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble comfort: O happy Woman, goe on a Gods name, and bee of good comfort, a ſonne of ſo many teares is impoſſible to periſh. And not long after, after ſo many pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, ſo many teares, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeeres, ſo much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie, feruency and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance, it pleaſed God hee became a Chriſtian, and one of the moſt vvorthy Fathers of the Church.</p>
            <p>Many haue I knowne powre out their prayers with teares to God, ten,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:21051:47" rendition="simple:additions"/>twenty yeeres together, and I haue heard longer, for the aſſurance of Gods loue towards them in Chriſt, and yet all that while haue not had their deſire. Which God doth partly to try vs, if wee will expect him with patience;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 11.5.</note> partly, to ſharpen vs the oftner and more feruently to inuoke him: partly, to<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.23. <hi>to the</hi> 28.</note> to exerciſe his gifts in vs: and yet in the end crowns his children with vnſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able conſolation: in the meane time giuing them Humilitie, and Patience, and Strength to await him.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:21051:48"/>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> 8. The laſt Ornament in this Sacrifice of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 70.4.</note> is the Crown of praiſe, wherewith euery one muſt bee adorned, that will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly offer their vowes to God.</p>
            <p>A Crowne of ſo ineſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable value, that GOD preferres it before all the burnt offerings of Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locks and Goats;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.</note> nay, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the Incenſe of <hi>Sheba,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69.31.</note> and the gold of <hi>Arabia.</hi> And for that cauſe it vvas hee ſo dearely loued <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> his Anointed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 96.98, 100, 101, 148, 149.</note> for that the praiſe of his God was alwayes in his mouth, and his tongue was euer tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:21051:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>of his righteouſneſſe. Euery night was he ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his mercies, and of his truth and iudgements continually.</p>
            <p>As there were three perſons in the Trinity that bleſſed him; ſo there were three parts in him by which hee returned his thankfulnes back againe: his heart, his tongue, his hand. And theſe three, like the Heauens, were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies in motion: his heart muſing, his glory ſinging that was his tongue, his hand warbling, one while on the Lute, then one the Cymballs, anon on other
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:21051:49"/>Inſtruments, Sackbuts &amp; Shawmes, Organs and Fifes; and the burthen of all was, <hi>Praiſe the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The bleſſing whereof redounded to himſelfe, and his, and crown'd him with ſuch both admirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and commendation, as hee reſts a patterne to the Saints of God, of all Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and goodnes, but ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of thankfulneſſe to the worlds end.</p>
            <p>In offering whereof, as he had the Spirt of God for his Author, to moue and rowze vp his Body &amp; Soule; ſo hee wanted not the examples of <hi>Noah,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:21051:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Deluge,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 8.21.</note> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whom God ſmelt a ſauour of reſt: Of <hi>Abraham,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 14.20</note> after his victory got of the 4. Kings. Of <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.</note> after <hi>Iſraels</hi> paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing thorow the Sea: Of <hi>Debora</hi> and <hi>Baruc,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iudg.</hi> 5.</note> when <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſera</hi> and <hi>Iabin</hi> were ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come; to teach him how, after his many deliueran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces from <hi>Sauls</hi> malicious and murtherous perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 21, 22, 23, 24.</note> from <hi>Abſaloms</hi> vnna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall and <hi>Achitophels</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>friendly and trecherous conſpiracies,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.11, 12.</note> from Gods ſharpe handling himſelfe and his people for <hi>Vriahs</hi> wife and life,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.10, 11.</note> hee ſhould with triumphall ſongs of
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:21051:50"/>acknowledgement bleſſe God, and expreſſe the vnfained thankfulneſſe of his heart for all the good turnes hee had receiued.</p>
            <p>Wherein, if wee right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſider of it, wee may ſoone ſee how God would by his example tutor vs, to let none of all thoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent and rich fauours, wherewith hee bleſſeth Mankinde generally, and his children in a far more particular ſort, to ſcape ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther our attentiue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation and meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of them, or our ſerious and true acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his loue, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:21051:50" rendition="simple:additions"/>him the intereſt which onely hee expects, and that is, the fruit of our lips, confeſſing his name,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hel.</hi> 13.15, 16.</note> which is our <hi>Orall</hi> Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Praiſe, &amp; the fruits of our Faith, in doing good, and relieuing the Saints, which is the <hi>Reall</hi> Sacrifice of our liues.</p>
            <p>For, as it's true which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſayes of Him,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.7.</note> that hee loues a cheerefull giuer, becauſe hee that giues ioyfully, ſhewes his readines to confeſſe from whom it is that hee hath meanes to giue; ſo is it as true, that hee loues as well a thankfull receiuer: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:21051:51"/>does any thing afflict him ſo, or cauſeth him vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſuch bitter complaints, as the ingratitude of ſuch for whom hee does moſt, yet they leaſt of all others regard him.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Num.</hi> 11.10. <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.11. <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.24. <hi>Exod.</hi> 16.3. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106.15, 26. <hi>Eſay.</hi> 1, 2, 3, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 4.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Let the often murmur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſart, and their often ſmart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for this very ſinne, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſo many, ſo grieuous plagues, his ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpbraid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of them by his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, calling Heauen and Earth to record againſt them; his many fearefull Iudgements powred vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the heads of vnthankfull men, euen Kings them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues;
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:21051:51" rendition="simple:additions"/>dethroning <hi>Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezzar,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.29.30.</note> ſtriking him with Madneſſe, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee forgate to bee thankfull to God, making him forget to bee King or Man;<note place="margin">2 <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 9.10</note> wounding that proud and ingratefull <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiochus</hi> ſo ſore, that hee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came loathſome to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: and vain-glorious <hi>Herod</hi> with ſuch a like diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 12.23.</note> cauſing vile wormes to deuoure him aliue, witneſſe vnto vs the truth heereof.</p>
            <p>They therefore whom God hath bleſſed with the fatneſſe of the Earth for their dwelling,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 27.39</note> and the
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:21051:52"/>dew of Heauen from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue, whoſe names and families he hath made ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, that their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers owne ſonnes, as well as ſtrangers,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 42.6.</note> bow downe yeelding reuerence vnto them, vpon whom he hath made the Spirit of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome &amp; counſell to reſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Numb.</hi> 11.25, 26.</note> whoſe loynes hee hath cloathed with health and ſtrength, whoſe hearts hee hath ſeaſoned with im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall grace, whoſe liues hee hath ſaued from the graue, from ſhame, who euery day ſtill haue their portion increaſed, muſt remember when they
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:21051:52" rendition="simple:additions"/>come, (and come they muſt often) to ſet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in the preſence of God, to giue him moſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fained &amp; particular thanks for their honour, their health, their riches,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 144.1, 2.</note> their knowledge, their faith, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouing it ſelfe by loue, their all other heauenly and earthly endowments, leſt elſe they be worſe then the very Beaſts, which fed by the hand of ſome lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Heard,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay.</hi> 1.3.</note> ceaſe not in their kind to ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues thankfull.</p>
            <p>It's reported of <hi>Plato,</hi> that euery day hee gaue God thankes for three
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:21051:53"/>things: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> That hee was borne a Man, not a Beaſt:<note place="margin">Plutarch. in Alcibi.</note> That hee was not borne a Barbarian, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> but a Grecian: And that hee was then borne, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> when hee might haue <hi>Socrates</hi> to teach him.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pamelius &amp; Beat. Rhena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus.</note>Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe was wont to praiſe God, for that he had made him a reaſonable man, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in the parts of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and ſoule, not lame, nor blind, nor fooliſh, as many be: for that hee had made him a Chriſtian man, no Pagan nor Iew: and for that he had made him a regenerate Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:21051:53" rendition="simple:additions"/>man, and a Biſhop a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Chriſtians, ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling him to teach both himſelfe &amp; others to liue and doe, as our Sauiour taught vs.</p>
            <p>Yea,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.25</note> our Sauiour him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in his owne Perſon, as of all other vertues and religious obedience, ſo heerein was pleaſed to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come our patterne.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 4.24.</note> And the bleſſed Apoſtles, by their preaching and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, nay, the ſenſible and ſenceleſſe Creatures may moue vs to care and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence in performance of it.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.1, 2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And ſurely, if wee giue
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:21051:54"/>but our eies leaue to view, or our eares to heare of thoſe infinite exceeding mercies, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> euery day &amp; night are dewed vpon vs, like the <hi>Manna</hi> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites</hi> in the deſart,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 16.14.</note> drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping as <hi>Hermon,</hi> vpon our ſoules, deliuerance fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bondage of ſin and Satan, comfort againſt the feare of eternall death, care to liue honeſtly and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly in the world, hope of a Crowne of glory in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptible, loue of Gods Word and his Saints here in earth; and vpon our bodies, health, ſtrength, rayment and food; or pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:21051:54" rendition="simple:additions"/>in the time of ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and want: On our names, children &amp; goods, preſeruation and increaſe; or elſe in the loſs of them, confidence and comfort, it is not poſſible, but the moſt inflexible Adaman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine heart will melt and be diſſolued into a Spring of thankfull and ioyfull teares, to conſider of the kindnes of our good God.</p>
            <p>Seeing then this is the ſoules rich attire, which makes her more beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in the ſight of God, when and whileſt ſhe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips before his foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoole, than the glittering
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:21051:55"/>ſtarres doe the Heauens in the night; let vs, in the very inſtant of praying; ſtriue againſt the dulneſſe of our fleſh, the vnwilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of nature, the hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our hearts, and the blindneſſe of mind, to bee ſoundly touch'd with the feeling and ſence of the want of ſuch things for which wee pray, as of the want of</p>
            <p>Sorrow for our ſinnes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.3, 4, 5.</note> originall, actuall, lately, or long ſince done againſt either God or Man,</p>
            <p>Sence of the decaying of ſauing grace in vs,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.12.</note> the comfort whereof we haue<note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.3.</note>
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:21051:55" rendition="simple:additions"/>had, and ſhould ſtill in our hearts,</p>
            <p>Faith in the promiſes of grace and life,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Mat.</hi> 14.30</note>
            </p>
            <p>Strength to withſtand our owne corruptions,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.10.</note> the Diuell and the worlds aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults,</p>
            <p>Patience and depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance on God in the time of triall,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 22, 57, 58, 60. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.35, 36. <hi>Conloſs.</hi> 1.11.</note> when tedious and ſharpe ſickneſſe, pouerty, reproch, diſobedience of children or ſeruants, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtick vntowardnes, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindneſſe of falſe-hearted friends, preſſures of migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty enemies, ſudden vnex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected dangers, impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, loſſe of goods, or
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:21051:56"/>any other vexation af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicts vs,</p>
            <p>The Spirit of Meeknes and Humility,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Philip.</hi> 2.8. <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.29</note> proud and towring minds that are euer climbing,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ipheſ.</hi> 4.2.</note> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer aſpiring after earthly things,</p>
            <p>Wiſdome and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in the myſteries of our Redemption,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.19 <hi>Coloſi.</hi> 1.9.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Conſtancie,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoc.</hi> 2.10.</note> in forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king &amp; ſtriving againſt ſin,</p>
            <p>Moderation in gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the rage of our Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ</hi> 4.26 31.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Sobrietie,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.15.</note> in taming our luſts and affections,</p>
            <p>Watchfulneſſe ouer our whole man,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.8.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:21051:56" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Care to pray often,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Coloſs.</hi> 4.2.</note> 
               <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.17.</p>
            <p>Zeale in Prayer,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.7.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Compaſſion of others miſery,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.15.</note> 
               <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.36.</p>
            <p>Obſeruing our continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſlips,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 119.59.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Meditation in the Law of God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 119.15.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Attentiueneſſe to the Word preached,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mal.</hi> 13.23</note>
            </p>
            <p>Serious conſideration of the ſhortneſſe of our life,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.10, 11. <hi>Iob.</hi> 14.1, 2, 3, 4, 5. <hi>Reu.</hi> 21. <hi>&amp;</hi> 22. <hi>Eſay</hi> 30.33</note> the vanity of all earthly things, the glory of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and the terrors of Hell-fire,</p>
            <p>Often and deepe think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Chriſts ſufferings and loue towards vs,</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:21051:57"/>
Diligence in marking how God deales,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 119.21.</note> and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes hath done with his children, with the wicked, with our ſelues;<note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.34. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 105. <hi>&amp;</hi> 106.</note> his bound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe pitty and mercy to ſome; his ſeuerity and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor vpon others; his howerly fauours vpon vs and ours,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 119.101.102.</note> in keeping vs from haynous and notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſinnes,</p>
            <p>Bettering vs by our ſinnes,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.11.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Helping vs againſt ſinnes,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.9.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Defending vs by his Angles,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.7.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Bleſſing our labours and Families,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 147.13, 14.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:21051:57" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Teaching vs to beare the croſſe patiently,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 16.33.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Helping vs when all meanes faile vs,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.12 13, 27.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Thankfulneſſe to God for euery bleſſing.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 146.1, 2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>For verily,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.26.</note> as S. <hi>Iames</hi> ſayes; <hi>Hee that ſeemeth to bee religious, and refrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth not his tongue, but deceiues his owne heart, his religion is but vaine:</hi> ſo hee that ſeems religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and prayeth with his tongue, not hauing in his heart a true feeling of his wants, hee deceiues him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and his prayer is but vaine: For the ſenſe of want to prayer, is like the
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:21051:58"/>ſpirit to the body.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 2.26.</note> The bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy without the ſpirit, is dead, feeles not the chains wherein it's bound, the wounds are made in it, the diſhonour done to it; ſo is prayer wihout ſence of want: It ſhewes not that the ſoule is aliue, gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vnder the Diuels yoke, the deepe wounds of ſinne; but like one that hath drunk much <hi>Oppium,</hi> deadly aſleep, if not ſtark dead: nay more; it's idle like the Heathe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s babbling to no end,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.7.</note> with many fond hypocriticall Ohs, and O Father, when it cannot tell what to aske the Father:
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:21051:58" rendition="simple:additions"/>Its vnprofitable, neither edifying him that makes it, nor thoſe that heare it: It's vnacceptable, being the Sacrifice of folly, and blaſphemous, raſhly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the moſt holy Names of God in vaine.</p>
            <p>Therefore, if wee finde not in the act of Praying, a quick ſenſe of our wants, yet, at leaſt, let vs haue and be deeply moued with the feeling of the want of fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, what ſpirituall helps our ſoules doe need.</p>
            <p>And then in the next place; let euery Sinner, as hee feeles himſelfe, either by nature or cuſtome,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:21051:59"/>moſt in clin'd to, or temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with any one ſinne, zealouſly &amp; ſtrongly pray againſt it:</p>
            <p>The Atheiſt againſt his blind and vnbeleeuing heart, that hee may ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge Gods power, infiniteneſſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.31.</note> mercie, wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, loue, iuſtice, good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, prouidence, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence euery where, ſeeing and ſearching all actions, all hearts, yea, the moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret thoughts of the ſoule, and ſo learne both to loue and feare him:</p>
            <p>The Idolaters and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 19.18, 19.</note> againſt their ſottiſh and ſenceleſſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:21051:59" rendition="simple:additions"/>of God in any image or viſible forme, or in praying to any ſaue him alone: in ſeeking to, or counſelling with Sorce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, Witches,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Chr.</hi> 33.12, 13.</note> Wiſe men (as they terme them) or any ſuch Helliſh and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden Art; that hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth they may ſerue him in ſpirit and truth:</p>
            <p>The blaſphemous ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, againſt his hearts corruptedneſſe and Hell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fir'd tongue;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 5.12.</note> that he may no more, either by feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſoule-tearing othes, or by mincing and ſmall ſlight ones (as they are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted, but falſly) pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:21051:60"/>the ſacred Name of God, who will not let that ſinne ſcape vnplagued;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.7.</note> but alwayes ſtriue both with his tongue and heart to bleſſe God, confeſſing his ſinne, and crying for pardon and grace to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend.</p>
            <p>The careleſſe prophane man,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 31.16, 17.</note> againſt his wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, in contemning Gods Worſhip, Word, Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Sabbath, Church, Prayers publike and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate, that he may learne to eſteeme of the knowledge of Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Philip.</hi> 3.7.8.</note> more then all the profits and pleaſures of the world,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.17.</note> and loue
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:21051:60" rendition="simple:additions"/>and reuerence thoſe that teach it.</p>
            <p>The diſſembling Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite, that makes a ſhew of Religion, and hath none, againſt his hollow, peruerſe and deceitfull heart, that hee may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a true practiſer of holineſſe in his life.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.22.</note> holineſſe in his life.</p>
            <p>The Voluptuous and vaine men,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 3.5, 6, 7</note> againſt their luſts, laſciuiouſneſſe, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleaneneſſe, adulreries, vanitie of ſpeech, attire, company and diſports, that they may redeeme the time they haue loſt, whileſt they walked in the wayes of their own hearts,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:21051:61"/>and ſo long as they liue, ſtudy to offer vp their ſoules and bodies vvith <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent ſacrifices to God.</p>
            <p>The Gluttonous and Drunkards,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.18</note> againſt their Epicuriſme, ſenſualitie, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatiable bibbing, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſiue abuſing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, their time, the Creatures, that they may learne in all ſobrietie and temperance to watch vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to prayer and faſting, leſt the vnclean ſpirit preuaile againſt them.</p>
            <p>The Ambitious and high-minded, againſt their Pride and Surquedry, that
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:21051:61" rendition="simple:additions"/>they may learne of Chriſt to become lowly and meeke in heart,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.29</note> and ſo finde reſt for their ſoules.</p>
            <p>The Couetous,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.5.</note> againſt their hard-heartedneſſe and want of Charitie, Faith, ans all other gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that ſith they are ſuch,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10.3.</note> as GOD abhorres them, they may bee filled with the bowels of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 3.12.</note> to pitie thoſe that want,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 19.8.</note> and reſtore againe their ill-gotten goods; that GOD in Chriſt may pitie them, and reſtore them to his fauour.</p>
            <p>The vnmercifull and
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:21051:62"/>cruell minded,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 6.36.</note> againſt their incredulous &amp; dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged churliſhneſſe, that GOD would turne their hearts to become merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.13.</note> leſt in the end they want mercy.</p>
            <p>The ſlanderous and ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing tongues,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.25.</note> againſt their delight in falſ-hood, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truthes, reproching and tales, that with <hi>Dauid</hi> they may haue a vvatch before them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 39.1, 2.</note> and that GOD would keepe the doore of their lips, tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching them to ſpeake the truth, and deteſt all lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings.</p>
            <p>The murtherer againſt
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:21051:62" rendition="simple:additions"/>his vnbrideled rage and paſsion,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 22.15.</note> and thirſting af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter bloud, that hee may learne to bee angry with his ſinne,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 5.6.</note> and thirſt after righteouſneſſe, and the Kingdome of God.</p>
            <p>The Thiefe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.28.</note> againſt I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleneſſe, Couetouſneſſe, and diſtruſt in God, that hee may learne to labour with his hands, prouiding for things honeſt lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in the ſight of God, and men, and relye vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the prouidence of God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 37.3.</note> vſing thoſe iuſt meanes which God hath appointed.</p>
            <p>The ignorant, againſt
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:21051:63"/>the ſluggiſhneſſe of their nature,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4.17, 118.</note> the darkneſſe and blindneſſe of their minde, that God would enligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten them with his Spirit of grace, and teach them how to ſerue him as they ought.</p>
            <p>They that liue in ſinne,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5.</note> and know it, yet repent not, againſt their infideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, impenitencie, and thraldome to their luſts, that being deliuered from the power of the Diuell, they may amend their liues, and ſinne no more.</p>
            <p>They that haue receiued great meaſure of grace,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.21, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2.</note> and decay in it, or abuſe
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:21051:63" rendition="simple:additions"/>it, againſt their negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, coldneſſe, forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, backſliding and falling away; that vvith <hi>Peter</hi> being raiſ'd through the Mercie of God, they may runne on ioyfully the race that is ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, not fainting any more, nor yeelding to temptation, but vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antly reſiſting the Diuell alwayes.</p>
            <p>They that by the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundance of bleſsings grow proud,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoc.</hi> 3.17, 18, 19.</note> puffed vp with the winde of their owne ſtrength, in regard of the greatneſſe of their Temporall ſtate, or of
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:21051:64"/>their knowledge and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall abilities in preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or praying, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gift, (as this ſinne of Pride is euer the ſoreſt, and moſt frequent aſſaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of all men indued with any eminent parts:) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their innated prone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to vanitie and vaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glory, ſelfe-loue, boaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and conceiting too highly of their own worth, that they may ſee from whom they haue receiued theſe bleſsings, and bee thankefull.</p>
            <p>Finally, all ſorts of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, whom God cals to repentance; let them, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:21051:64" rendition="simple:additions"/>feeling the miſery they are in, and the want of that grace, whereby they that grace, whereby they muſt be helped, earneſtly and feruently cry for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 2.37.</note> with a reſolution to ſinne no more;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 38.11, 23.</note> with a full purpoſe euer after to walk in holineſſe and newneſſe of life,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.28.</note> for that is to pray with faith: with an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt endeuour to forſake ſinne: for elſe they doe but mock God: referring themſelues, and their ſuite to his pleaſure: for they muſt limit him no time to anſwere them: and as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſuch things as are lawfull to aske, and to a
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:21051:65"/>lawfull end, for other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they aske amiſſe, and their ſuite ſhall not bee granted.</p>
            <p>That they may not aske amiſſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.5.</note> let them aske in faith, beholding and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the promiſes of God, of life and ſaluation in Chriſt Ieſus: And let them try their faith by their purpoſe of neuer ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning againſt God againe, ſo far as their knowledge and power wil ſerue them: for that's an in fallible note of true faith; becauſe pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of liuing &amp; continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in ſin, is cleane contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to the nature of faith.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:21051:65" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Thus when the ſence of our want hath kindled in vs a flaming deſire to craue reliefe, and deſire hath awakened our ſleepie and fainting faith, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold and truſt in Gods promiſed mercies; Faith then muſt haue recourſe to God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.18.</note> and ſue for help and comfort at his hands: I ſay, at his hands: not at any creatures. For crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, be they Saints,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.37, 38.</note> bee they Angels, are not that Fountain of liuing waters, wherewith our thirſty ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits muſt be que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ched: But <hi>he alone</hi> who is <hi>the Father of lights,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.17.</note> 
               <hi>fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whom comes down
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:21051:66"/>euery good and perfect gift:</hi> who though hee bee high and excellent, dwelling in the light and holy place, ſo that no mortall eye can ſee him; yet hath hee li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſed vs that be but <hi>duſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.19.</note> to behold him with the Eye of Faith: which how weake ſo euer it be, ſo long as it is true and liuing, lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing God, and deſiring ſtill to be at peace vvith him, endeauouring in thoughts, words &amp; workes to pleaſe Him, euer fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt inward ſinnes and feares; outward al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lurements, and both in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward &amp; outward aſſaults,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:21051:66" rendition="simple:additions"/>is not reiected: neither yet receiued for it owne ſake, but for <hi>the merit and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe of Chriſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 16.23. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.12.</note> 
               <hi>For as yet it's imperfect, beleeuing but in part.</hi> Therefore in Chriſts mediation let it come, not in the bleſſed Virgin <hi>Maries,</hi> nor any Saints:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.3.</note> for their bloud purged vs not from ſinne, neither haue we through them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.2.</note> 
               <hi>acceſſe</hi> to the Throne of God, but onely by <hi>Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.18.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And this is that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable Comfort, which fraile man, through the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Gods loue,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.15</note> hath left him, as a ſure refuge
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:21051:67"/>againſt all doubts. Of himſelfe, hee is the vtter enemie of God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.5.</note> borne in ſinne: full of ſinne: to be damned for ſinne,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.17.</note> vnleſſe he finde a ſufficient Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to make Gods Iuſtice ſatisfaction:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.29.</note> For God is a conſuming fire againſt ſinne, not enduring the leaſt darkneſſe of it to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proch him. How then ſhould hee dare, ſince the Holy glorious Seraphims are ſaid with their wings to hide their face vvhen they praiſe God, to looke vpon the face of his offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Maker? Behold heere the bounty and loue of
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:21051:67" rendition="simple:additions"/>God: Hee hath ſo loued Man,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.16.</note> that hee hath giuen him his owne Sonne to redeeme him: His Sonne hath ſo redeemed him, that now God is pleaſed for his Sonnes ſake to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, nay,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 55.1.</note> to command man to come to him. not aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king any other ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 2.37.</note> but <hi>onely</hi> to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent and beleeue in him.</hi> That he may repent, hee giues him the Miniſterie of the Word of Life,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.30.</note> and the power of his Spirit to ſhew him his ſinnes, vvith the vglineſſe and danger of them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.104.</note> that he may hate them. And leaſt the grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſneſſe
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:21051:68"/>and multitudes of them ſhould cauſe him deſpaire of pardon for them;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.11.</note> hee begets in him Faith, to beleeue thoſe promiſes of remiſsion and life,<note place="margin">12,</note> which in his Sonne <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> he hath made him.<note place="margin">13.</note> Hee ſtrengthens him to lay hold vpon thoſe promiſes, and apply them particularly to himſelfe: thus:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whoſoeuer beleeues in Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 3.16.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall not periſh, but ſhall haue life euerlaſting:</hi> But I beleeue in Chriſt, therefore I ſhall not pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, but haue life euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:21051:68" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Againe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whoſoeuer hungers and thirſts after righteouſneſse,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.6.</note> 
               <hi>is bleſsed, and ſhall bee ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I Hunger and thirſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter righteouſneſſe. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhall be ſatisfied, and I am bleſſed.</p>
            <p>Againe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He that beleeues in Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 6.47.</note> 
               <hi>though he were dead, yet ſhall he liue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I beleeue in Chriſt, though I was dead in ſinne: Therefore though I was dead, yet ſhall I liue.</p>
            <p>Againe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hee that beleeues that Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.15.</note>
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:21051:69"/>
               <hi>Christ is the Sonne of God, hath euerlaſting life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I beleeue that he is ſo: Therefore I haue euerlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing life.</p>
            <p>When all this is done, God then forceth him, though fearfull, and back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and doubting at firſt, by the power of his Spirit to come in the Name of his Son Chriſt, with boldneſſe, comfort and Hope, before him, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiues him to grace, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts his confeſsion, puts away his ſinne, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ables him to grow and goe on in goodneſſe: and all this, for the loue hee
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:21051:69" rendition="simple:additions"/>beares vs in his Sonne. O the infinit vnſpeakeable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of that loue! O the monſtrous ingratitude of that man that will ſeeke to others, and not to God, or if to God, by others, and not by Chriſt!</p>
            <p>To end this point of our dutie in praying; let vs, hauing powred out our hearts vnto God, in ſuch a manner as hath beene ſhewed, beware we faint not in continuing to call and cry to him ſtill; though for a while hee ſeeme to repell vs:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36.8.</note> for ſure hee will heare vs, though he hold vs off: Hee graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:21051:70"/>at laſt will turne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, as Chriſt did to the two blind men,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.32 <hi>Mar.</hi> 10.49 <hi>Luke</hi> 18.39, 40.</note> and heale our wounded, diſeaſed ſoules; infuſing them with the life of grace, ſpeaking peace to our ſpirits, as he did to <hi>Dauid,</hi> and make vs know hee is become our ſaluation.</p>
            <p>And ſince the number of his mercies vpon vs are like the number of the Starres,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 71.15.</note> of the Sands, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to be counted for their multitude, or valued for their worth; let our Praiſes flye vp perpetually to Heauen, like thoſe fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grant and ſweet-ſmelling
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:21051:70" rendition="simple:additions"/>Odours of <hi>Arabia:</hi> the ſent whereof will ſo delight him, that he vvil make our ſoules, his Sanctuary; our hearts, his holy habitation and reſting place; our names precious; our liues good, and our end happy: when hauing loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the bonds of mortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, vnder which, wee are euer groaning here, hee ſhall ſet vs with the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, to praiſe him euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtingly, in the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his preſence,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 21.24.</note> where nothing elſe is done, but ſinging,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 4.8.</note> and bleſsing of his name for euer.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:21051:71"/>
After wee haue thus made our Sacrifice of Prayer, wee muſt not ſo reſt, as if all were done: But that it may be profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to vs,</p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 146.5, 6, 7, 8, 9. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145. 18, 19, 20.</note> wee muſt haue a particular conſtant Faith, to beleeue that God can and will accompliſh our requeſts.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 138.7, 8.</note> That hee can; becauſe of his Ominipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tencie: That he will;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 88.13.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of his Promiſe: O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, if wee wauer, if wee doubt, if we faint, it ſhewes our Diſtruſtfulnes, if not of his Power, at leaſt of his Mercy,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.5, 6, 7.</note> and then we ſhall receiue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:21051:71" rendition="simple:additions"/>at his hands.</p>
            <p>Next, looke vvhat Grace wee pray for,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.101.</note> or what corruptions we pray againſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.22.23.</note> wee muſt <hi>ſtriue earneſtly</hi> to attaine the one, and <hi>carefully watch</hi> yo auoid the other, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing all good and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full meanes, ordained and allowed by God to that end.</p>
            <p>Hee that prayes for knowledge in the Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of our Redemption, muſt giue himſelfe to Reading, Study,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.16.</note> Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation: and if hee be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned, to hearing of the Preachers, and confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:21051:72"/>with ſuch as are able to teach him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.17.</note> yet not neglecting his voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and charge.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.8.</note>
            </p>
            <p>He that prayes againſt the ſinnes of his heart and life,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39.1.</note> muſt flye all occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons may make him ſinne: elſe hee ſhall meerely by praying mocke God, and moſt fondly delude him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amos</hi> 4.4, 5.</note>
            </p>
            <p>When <hi>Dauid</hi> ſo deſired to be ſaued from his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, hee ranne not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuouſly into their hands, but warily kept himſelfe out of view: And when <hi>Paul</hi> charged the <hi>Epheſians</hi> to be feruent in<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.18.</note>
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:21051:72" rendition="simple:additions"/>Prayer, that they may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound in <hi>all grace;</hi> he gaue them no libertie to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany with ſuch as might withdraw them from pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to ſinne; but ſtraight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly charged them, and Saint <hi>Iude</hi> doth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iude</hi> 23. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5.</note> whereby they might bee drawne to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend.</p>
            <p>Heere, therefore, it is needfull, if we would haue and good by our Prayers, carefully to keepe theſe few rules.</p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.12, 13.</note> to mark the ſinnes againſt which wee haue prayed, and the Diuels ſubtill practice, either ſtill
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:21051:73"/>to continue them, or ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing forſaken them, to fall to them againe.</p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 3.6, 7, 8.</note> our frailety in reſiſting, and our rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe in yeelding to temptations offered.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.4.</note> the cuſtoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble diſpoſition of our hearts, in our paſsions and affections of Ioy, Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, Anger, Feare, Hope, Loue, and how they ſway vs.</p>
            <p>Fourthly,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 11.59.</note> the effect of thoſe Paſsions in our liues, publiquely in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany; priuately in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany; priuately, at home; with our Wiues, Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, Seruants, Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours;
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:21051:73" rendition="simple:additions"/>and more priuately with our ſelues, when wee are retyred.</p>
            <p>To preuent and foyle the Diuell,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.8, 9.</note> wee muſt vſe Sobriety, Watchfulneſſe, often &amp; feruent prayers in our heart: which though they bee but ſhort, ſuch as this, O my God, let me not bee ouercome of this temptation.</p>
            <p>Lord, be thou my help, for I truſt in thee.</p>
            <p>Forſake mee not, O God: leaue me not to my ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Giue mee vnderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and power to doe thy will.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="138" facs="tcp:21051:74"/>
Knit my heart vnto thee, that I may feare thy Name, and ſuch like: yet they are ſo powerfull, that they put the Diuell to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trait and foyle, at leaſt for a time.</p>
            <p>To take heed our hearts,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39.1. <hi>Pro.</hi> 23.26. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.55.</note> which beyond meaſure are deceitfull, deceiue vs not; wee muſt alwayes haue a guard vpon them: ſaying to our ſelues, O heart, thou ſhouldeſt bee the Temple of my Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers moſt holy Spirit: why the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doeſt thou harbor theſe wicked thoughts? &amp; then further ſay, Cleanſe thy houſe, deare Sauiour,
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:21051:74" rendition="simple:additions"/>that thou mayeſt euer dwell with mee.</p>
            <p>To keepe vs from no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious and ſcandalous ſinnes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.21, 22. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.63. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.101.</note> wee muſt boldly breake from, and leaue off all company and occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to defile vs: If that cannot be, either in regard of command wee are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to, or other circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances that cannot bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoided;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.158.</note> let not our hearts nor tongues giue conſent, but our eyes bee like <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uids,</hi> guſhing out, when wee are at libertie, ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of Teares, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waile both their,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.136.</note> and our owne frailetie.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:21051:75"/>
To preſerue vs from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen and ſecret Atheiſme, Diſtruſt, Deſpayre, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, Blaſphemy, Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, Idolatry, and neglect of ſeruing God, and all ſinnes directly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the firſt Table: re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member in our Hearts, in our lips, in our liues, to bee holy as our Heauenly. Father is,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.48.</note> knowing hee hates the ſinnes of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfulneſſe, abhorres the wickednes of tongue and lips,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 6.16, 17, 18.</note> and vpon wicked and prophane liuers will raine downe the portion they ſhall haue to drink,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 11.6.</note> ſtorms and tempeſt, and anguiſh
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:21051:75" rendition="simple:additions"/>of Soule,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 20.15.</note> and fire &amp; brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone in Hell-fire.</p>
            <p>To preſerue vs from vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe in our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation, and the breach of charity to our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours in our liues, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member alwayes to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Chriſts rule:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.12.</note> Doe as thou wouldſt bee done to; and what thou wouldeſt not be done to, doe not. And Saint <hi>Pauls, So runne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.24.</note> 
               <hi>that thou maiſt obtaine a Crowne of righteouſneſſe.</hi> And Saint <hi>Iohns, Hee that loues not his brother,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.20.</note> 
               <hi>loues not God:</hi> And forget not Saint <hi>Iames,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 2.18.</note> 
               <hi>Shew me thy faith by thy workes:</hi> for, <hi>by
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:21051:76"/>them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.8, 9, 10.</note> ſaies Saint <hi>Peter, thou muſt make thy vocation and election ſure,</hi> Elſe thy pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and thy faith, and thy ſelfe are but dead, and vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly vnacceptable in the ſight of God.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, wee muſt keepe our ſoules in a dayly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of all theſe ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall exerciſes, taming the rebelliouſnes of our fleſh by Faſting, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> did,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.27.</note> when wee finde our ſelues preſſed with dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.3.</note> and ſloth, or vnwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſſe,<note place="margin">20.</note> or vanity: ſo will our ſpirits grow nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and quicke to call on God,<note place="margin">21.</note> our hearts ſoft
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:21051:76" rendition="simple:additions"/>and tender to mourne, our Prayers ſo feruent, that God will heare them, and our Praiſes ſo accepted, that he will reward them.</p>
            <p>That God which by the bloud of his Son hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed vs, enable vs by his Spirit, through the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings of his Sonne, to practiſe effectually all theſe things. <hi>Amen.</hi> To him be glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and praiſe for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more. (⸪)</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
